<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Light Focus' Blog</title>
    <description>' OR 1=1; --</description>
    <link>/</link>
    <atom:link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Mon, 22 Nov 2021 21:17:01 +0800</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 22 Nov 2021 21:17:01 +0800</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v4.2.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Messing around with USBC on RX 6800</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;With the release of the AMD RX 6800 series, we finally have USB Type-C support on AMD GPU while macOS added the support for Rx 6800 series in 11.4.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re using RX 6800 as previous AMD cards in Hackintosh, namely config WhateverGreen, you’ll find it works as expected. One problem is obviously the USB Type-C port on the back can only be used as a video output and power output.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To find out why, I took a look at my PCIe devices list.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lightfocus-1256547063.cos.ap-hongkong.myqcloud.com/posts/usbc/Screen%20Shot%202021-11-22%20at%205.08.05%20PM.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we can see, in the devices that are under vendor name AMD, we sure can find something like the USB controller.
But if we check out the USB controller section, we can only see the one that’s provided by the motherboard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For now, it’s pretty clear that Apple didn’t do a great job “supporting” this card. This card works as expected, built-in USB controller can be detected, however, macOS failed to pair it with a normal USB controller, instead, it’s paired with AppleAMDUSBXHCIPCI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lightfocus-1256547063.cos.ap-hongkong.myqcloud.com/posts/usbc/Screen%20Shot%202021-11-22%20at%205.02.44%20PM.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To solve this prolem, I grabed a copy of XHCI-unsupported.kext and modified it into forcing use AppleUSBXHCISPT.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lightfocus-1256547063.cos.ap-hongkong.myqcloud.com/posts/usbc/Screen%20Shot%202021-11-22%20at%209.12.58%20PM.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By doing so, we’re able to see a new USB controller in Hackintool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lightfocus-1256547063.cos.ap-hongkong.myqcloud.com/posts/usbc/Screen%20Shot%202021-11-22%20at%209.15.55%20PM.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And with test, I can confirm that the data function of USB is working correctly on that port.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 22 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>/Messing-Around-with-USBC-on-RX6800/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/Messing-Around-with-USBC-on-RX6800/</guid>
        
        <category>Gear</category>
        
        
        <category>Hardware</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Tamron 28-200mm Long Term Review</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I bought the Tamron 28-200mm f/2.8-5.6 back in January and have been using it since then. Now more than half a year passed, I think it’s a good time that I write a long-term review for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my early career in photography, I was told not to buy these kinds of super zoom lenses as they tend to perform badly. When I was checking out the review of this lens, however, many reviewers say that it performs “not like a super zoom lens” which caught my attention. Before switching to the Sony system again, I went to Chongqing and realized how important a telephoto lens is in travel photography. I do not want a dedicated telephoto lens as they’re heavy, that’s why I decided to give this 28-200mm lens a go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Compared to other competitors on the market, the Tamron 28-200mm has some pros and cons. It’s compact, lightweight, and relatively cheap with a brighter than normal aperture. But it lacks 24mm and image stabilization got some criticize. To me, its pros outweigh its cons, so it should serve me well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before having this lens, what I would take with me was usually a 24-105mm lens so having 105-200mm is a huge benefit. This means I can take pictures of subjects that are far away thereby eliminate distraction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lightfocus-1256547063.cos.ap-hongkong.myqcloud.com/gallery/2021/DSC02009.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lightfocus-1256547063.cos.ap-hongkong.myqcloud.com/gallery/2021/DSC02952.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lightfocus-1256547063.cos.ap-hongkong.myqcloud.com/gallery/2021/DSC02957.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lightfocus-1256547063.cos.ap-hongkong.myqcloud.com/gallery/2021/DSC03153.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lightfocus-1256547063.cos.ap-hongkong.myqcloud.com/gallery/2021/DSC03582.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, telephoto lenses do more than that, it also compresses the scene and makes it dramatic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lightfocus-1256547063.cos.ap-hongkong.myqcloud.com/gallery/2021/DSC01713.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lightfocus-1256547063.cos.ap-hongkong.myqcloud.com/gallery/2021/DSC03169.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lightfocus-1256547063.cos.ap-hongkong.myqcloud.com/gallery/2021/DSC03376.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This lens also provides some sort of macro capability which makes it suitable for some product shots.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lightfocus-1256547063.cos.ap-hongkong.myqcloud.com/gallery/2021/DSC01450.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lightfocus-1256547063.cos.ap-hongkong.myqcloud.com/gallery/2021/Keyboard.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lightfocus-1256547063.cos.ap-hongkong.myqcloud.com/gallery/2021/DSC01984.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lightfocus-1256547063.cos.ap-hongkong.myqcloud.com/gallery/2021/PEN-F.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lightfocus-1256547063.cos.ap-hongkong.myqcloud.com/gallery/2021/DSC03010.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lightfocus-1256547063.cos.ap-hongkong.myqcloud.com/gallery/2021/DSC03107.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While we lose that 24mm focal length, we do get a brighter aperture which makes a difference when you’re shooting in a dark situation and you need that shutter speed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lightfocus-1256547063.cos.ap-hongkong.myqcloud.com/gallery/2021/DSC03482.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lightfocus-1256547063.cos.ap-hongkong.myqcloud.com/gallery/2021/DSC03486.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lightfocus-1256547063.cos.ap-hongkong.myqcloud.com/gallery/2021/DSC03531.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since it has a zoom range from 28mm to 200mm, you can make different compositions in a scene without swapping the lens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lightfocus-1256547063.cos.ap-hongkong.myqcloud.com/gallery/2021/DSC01899.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lightfocus-1256547063.cos.ap-hongkong.myqcloud.com/gallery/2021/DSC01934.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lightfocus-1256547063.cos.ap-hongkong.myqcloud.com/gallery/2021/DSC01987.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lightfocus-1256547063.cos.ap-hongkong.myqcloud.com/gallery/2021/DSC01999.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lightfocus-1256547063.cos.ap-hongkong.myqcloud.com/gallery/2021/DSC02465.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lightfocus-1256547063.cos.ap-hongkong.myqcloud.com/gallery/2021/DSC02482.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lightfocus-1256547063.cos.ap-hongkong.myqcloud.com/gallery/2021/DSC03194.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lightfocus-1256547063.cos.ap-hongkong.myqcloud.com/gallery/2021/DSC03340.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sharpness-wise, I found it adequate for the 42-megapixel sensor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lightfocus-1256547063.cos.ap-hongkong.myqcloud.com/gallery/2021/DSC01991.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This image is cropped to 5.5 megapixels and it’s still usable for social media sharing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Admittedly, Sony 24-105mm gives you more resolution but it’s more heavy and expensive, not to mention the abbreviated zoom range.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lack of image stabilization means you need to rely on the IBIS and let’s be honest, Sony’s IBIS is very poor. For me with multiple tires and errors, I can make 1/30s at 200mm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider its price, quality, and size, I do not have any complaints about it. However, I would recommend the Tamron 17-28 f/2.8 as a complement to it and with 17-200mm, you’re pretty much covered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bonus: Some photos took with 17-28mm&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lightfocus-1256547063.cos.ap-hongkong.myqcloud.com/gallery/2021/DSC02895.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lightfocus-1256547063.cos.ap-hongkong.myqcloud.com/gallery/2021/DSC03065.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lightfocus-1256547063.cos.ap-hongkong.myqcloud.com/gallery/2021/DSC03260.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lightfocus-1256547063.cos.ap-hongkong.myqcloud.com/gallery/2021/DSC03292.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 11 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>/Tamron-28-200-Review/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/Tamron-28-200-Review/</guid>
        
        <category>Gear</category>
        
        
        <category>Photography</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Revisit on Photography Gears I've Used</title>
        <description>&lt;h1&gt;You can find photos I took &lt;a href=&quot;/gallery&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started photography back in late 2014 when I picked up gears my dad no longer uses. I had a Nikon D200 and three lenses: Nikon 17-35mm f/2.8D, Nikon 80-200mm f/2.8D, and Nikon 105mm f/2.8G Micro.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: center; width: 100%;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lightfocus-1256547063.cos.ap-hongkong.myqcloud.com/posts/photo-gears/D200.jpg&quot; style=&quot;margin: 0 auto; width: 50%;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: center; width: 100%;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lightfocus-1256547063.cos.ap-hongkong.myqcloud.com/posts/photo-gears/17-35.jpg&quot; style=&quot;margin: 0 auto; width: 50%;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: center; width: 100%;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lightfocus-1256547063.cos.ap-hongkong.myqcloud.com/posts/photo-gears/80-200.jpg&quot; style=&quot;margin: 0 auto; width: 50%;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: center; width: 100%;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lightfocus-1256547063.cos.ap-hongkong.myqcloud.com/posts/photo-gears/105.jpg&quot; style=&quot;margin: 0 auto; width: 50%;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although they were already pretty outdated back in 2014, they taught me the basics of photography, things like aperture, shutter speed, and ISO.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used D200 for a little more than half a year and took some pictures of landscapes, flowers, and black-headed gulls that migration to Kunming (where I live) every year. The D200 only has 10 megapixels and the back LCD screen is very low-res, so I couldn’t check if my photos were in focus or if there was any motion blur. Meanwhile, I’m in the early stage of photography, so I’m satisfied with a few photos taken on D200.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In June 2015, I got the chance for a new camera. Since I’m on a budget, I got myself an entry-level full-frame camera with a kit lens: Nikon D610 and Nikon 24-120mm f/4G.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: center; width: 100%;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lightfocus-1256547063.cos.ap-hongkong.myqcloud.com/posts/photo-gears/D610.jpg&quot; style=&quot;margin: 0 auto; width: 50%;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: center; width: 100%;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lightfocus-1256547063.cos.ap-hongkong.myqcloud.com/posts/photo-gears/24-120.jpg&quot; style=&quot;margin: 0 auto; width: 50%;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why a full-frame camera and a standard zoom lens you may ask? Full frame camera was of course for really making use of these full-frame lenses, I never knew what 17mm was like on full-frame. As for the standard zoom lens, I really needed a one-lens solution when I went out. I usually needed to carry two lenses, because 17-35mm was a little bit limiting on the long end. I also tried a flash but didn’t quite get the hang of how to use flash.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before high school graduation in June 2016, I mainly used this camera for events in high school, although I did take it on a trip to Thailand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During high school, I learned the basics of photography and my camera captured so much precious memory. Since I didn’t have spare time, my skills didn’t quite level-up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My high school was pretty close to my home so bringing a DSLR (Digital Single-lens Reflex Camera) to school wasn’t a huge deal. But my university was quite far from my home plus we didn’t have many class events going on so I wasn’t willing to take my camera there. I took way fewer photos during 2016-2017 and that’s why I decided to sell some gears I didn’t use much. I ended up keeping only the 24-120mm and 80-200mm. By the way, I used the money I got from selling those gears for a new MacBook Pro and that was probably one of the best purchases I ever made.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I went to Japan in the summer of 2017 and before that trip, I purchased a Nikon 50mm f/1.8G as a supplement of 24-120mm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: center; width: 100%;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lightfocus-1256547063.cos.ap-hongkong.myqcloud.com/posts/photo-gears/50%201.8.jpg&quot; style=&quot;margin: 0 auto; width: 50%;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was my first time using a prime lens (except that macro lens). However, unlike many other people, I didn’t get blown away by that shallow depth of field, but I did like the compactness of the prime lenses. As for the trip, I had to admit that Japan is a fantastic place for taking photos, I took quite a few great photos there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only problem I had was, after carrying the camera in a bag with a rather poorly-design load system, I started to feel that DSLR was too bulky. That’s when I turned my focus on mirrorless cameras.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wasn’t quite sure about the image quality of mirrorless cameras. Therefore, the first thought that struck me was buying a mirrorless camera as a back-up camera so that whenever I needed to travel light, I took the mirrorless camera.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a little bit of research, I came to the conclusion that mirrorless cameras are as good as DSLRs in most aspects. So I decided to ditch all my camera gears in exchange for the mirrorless system. I decided to go for Sony APS-C (Advanced Photo System type-C) cameras because I heard they have the best AF (Auto Focus) system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the cold winter of 2018, I cleared out all my gears and brought a Sony A6300 with Sony 16-50mm f/3.5-5.6 kit lens and a second-hand Zeiss Batis 25mm f/2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: center; width: 100%;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lightfocus-1256547063.cos.ap-hongkong.myqcloud.com/posts/photo-gears/A6300.jpeg&quot; style=&quot;margin: 0 auto; width: 50%;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: center; width: 100%;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lightfocus-1256547063.cos.ap-hongkong.myqcloud.com/posts/photo-gears/25%202.jpg&quot; style=&quot;margin: 0 auto; width: 50%;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Carrying a camera wasn’t a pain anymore. However, there are some compromises. Since the camera is quite small, the handling and the battery life are quite worse compared to DSLR. What’s also interesting was that I didn’t quite like the EVF (Electronic Viewfinder) at first. I felt it’s very low-res compared to OVF (Optical Viewfinder) so I wasn’t confident about the image I took until I saw the photos on my computer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that Zeiss lens became a 35mm-ish equivalent lens on an APS-C camera and I quickly fall in love with the 35mm focal length. After a while with this lens, I felt like this lens was a kind of waste on an APS-C camera. So I sold it and got myself a Sigma 16mm f/1.4 and a better Sony 18-135mm f/3.5-5.6 kit lens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: center; width: 100%;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lightfocus-1256547063.cos.ap-hongkong.myqcloud.com/posts/photo-gears/18-135.jpg&quot; style=&quot;margin: 0 auto; width: 50%;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That 18-135mm lens was a newly released one at the time so it’s sharp for a travel zoom lens. The best part was, this lens was sold as a kit lens with A6300 so you could get an amazing price if you buy the open-box version. I really liked this lens, compact, great zoom range, relatively sharp, and has some macro capability. The only downside I would say is the slow maximum aperture so I had to crank my ISO up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: center; width: 100%;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lightfocus-1256547063.cos.ap-hongkong.myqcloud.com/posts/photo-gears/16%201.4.jpg&quot; style=&quot;margin: 0 auto; width: 50%;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Sigma 16mm prime is also pretty good. This is my first time using an f/1.4 lens and I was often amazed by the low ISO value I could shoot with. Nevertheless, it’s kind of bulky on an APS-C camera.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I took these two lenses to Thailand (again) in 2018 and they served me just right. I had no complaint whatsoever about them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we all know what’s wrong with Sony APS-C cameras. They don’t have good color science, lack a front control dial and most importantly, there aren’t many APS-C lenses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Naturally, I looked for Fujifilm cameras as they have good color and probably the most extensive line of APS-C lenses. I got a Fujifilm X-T2 alone with a wide-angle Fujifilm 10-24mm f/4 lens and a Fujifilm 35mm f/1.4 lens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: center; width: 100%;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lightfocus-1256547063.cos.ap-hongkong.myqcloud.com/posts/photo-gears/X-T2.jpg&quot; style=&quot;margin: 0 auto; width: 50%;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Granted, many people liked Fujifilm for its retro design and its film simulation. However, I didn’t think they’re overwhelmingly better than the competitions. That retro design means no large grip and ok-ish handling. The X-Trans sensor Fujifilm uses, I actually found it has an impact on the fine detail on my images. If you zoom in, you’ll find some worm-like patterns. Moreover, since I shoot only RAW, good color means little to nothing for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: center; width: 100%;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lightfocus-1256547063.cos.ap-hongkong.myqcloud.com/posts/photo-gears/35%201.4.jpg&quot; style=&quot;margin: 0 auto; width: 50%;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be fair, that 35mm 1.4 lens is very compact and produces some amazing photos. The only disadvantage would be that slow and noisy AF system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: center; width: 100%;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lightfocus-1256547063.cos.ap-hongkong.myqcloud.com/posts/photo-gears/10-24.jpg&quot; style=&quot;margin: 0 auto; width: 50%;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for the 10-24mm lens, I think there is nothing to write home about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I was not happy about the image quality of the Fujifilm camera, I quickly sold it after only about 4 months of use. And this time I wanted to try a full-frame mirrorless camera.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, my budget was tight so I could only get a Sony A7R2 and a Sony 24-105mm f/4 lens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: center; width: 100%;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lightfocus-1256547063.cos.ap-hongkong.myqcloud.com/posts/photo-gears/A7R2.jpg&quot; style=&quot;margin: 0 auto; width: 50%;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The A7R2 was criticized for many things like its short battery life and slow AF, but at least it got that 42 megapixels sensor. I got to say its image quality blew me away. From high ISO to dynamic range, everything that comes from that sensor is simply amazing. Ok, maybe not the color. But you did feel all those shortcomings of A7R2 whenever you use it. Since I mainly shoot landscapes and slice of life, I didn’t bother too much by the AF speed. Just bring an extra battery and you’ll just be fine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: center; width: 100%;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lightfocus-1256547063.cos.ap-hongkong.myqcloud.com/posts/photo-gears/S24-105.jpg&quot; style=&quot;margin: 0 auto; width: 50%;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s talk about that 24-105mm lens for a while. Simply put, it’s the best 24-105mm lens on the market. It’s very sharp, focuses quickly, and has a better minimal focus distance which means it’s useful when you want to shoot some small objects. Unfortunately, it’s also a tad expensive than the competitions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember how I liked the 35mm focal length when I used the Zeiss lens? Well, I thought it’s a good time to introduce myself with the 35mm focal length again so I brought a Sony 35mm f/2.8 ZA lens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: center; width: 100%;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lightfocus-1256547063.cos.ap-hongkong.myqcloud.com/posts/photo-gears/35%202.8.jpg&quot; style=&quot;margin: 0 auto; width: 50%;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apart from 35mm, I brought it for its extremely compact size. F/2.8 may sound slow for a prime lens but really, I didn’t need the shallow depth of field and the camera has good high ISO performance. Anyway, it quickly became the go-to lens for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By far, I’ve used both APS-C and full-frame systems, but there was one thing left, M43 (Micro Four-Thirds). I was interested in this system when I did the research for mirrorless cameras back in late 2017, but I never really fall for it fearing its small sensor size would have too much impact on the image quality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One day, I came across a photographer online that used purely M43 cameras. I really like his photos and found no sign of unacceptable image quality. After reading his blog and did some research myself, I did something that sounds crazy. I sold my full-frame camera and brought an M43 camera.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had two choices at the time with identical price points: Olympus E-M1 Mark II or Panasonic G9. I ended up choosing the latter one for its better video capability. The funny thing was, I never shot a single video on G9 but the G9 tended to be the model with more resell value half a year later so I do not regret it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: center; width: 100%;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lightfocus-1256547063.cos.ap-hongkong.myqcloud.com/posts/photo-gears/G9.jpeg&quot; style=&quot;margin: 0 auto; width: 50%;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Together with G9 were two lenses: Panasonic Leica 12-60mm f/2.8-4 and Panasonic 45-150mm f/4-5.6.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: center; width: 100%;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lightfocus-1256547063.cos.ap-hongkong.myqcloud.com/posts/photo-gears/12-60.jpg&quot; style=&quot;margin: 0 auto; width: 50%;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The very first thing I found out was that 12-60mm on the G9 is fantastic. The SOOC (Straight Out of Camera) color is the best I’ve ever seen. This lens also has a shocking 0.6x maximum magnification on the telephoto end so it could act as a macro lens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: center; width: 100%;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lightfocus-1256547063.cos.ap-hongkong.myqcloud.com/posts/photo-gears/45-150.jpg&quot; style=&quot;margin: 0 auto; width: 50%;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 45-150mm was also very useful, it was very affordable while providing the 300mm equivalent field of view. Albeit slow as far as the aperture is concerned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now let’s talk about things I never experienced on previous cameras. First is that fully articulating screen. It’s very useful when you want to shoot from different angles although sometimes the traditional tilt screen may be more useful. The second is IBIS (In-body Image Stabilization), A7R2 has this but it’s lackluster. The IBIS on G9 is insane, I could handheld the camera for two seconds and still get sharp images. This is simply out of question on A7R2. Due to the longer exposure time, I found myself uses ISO 200 quite often, so the weak high ISO performance of M43 cameras is kind of eliminated here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be honest, M43 systems are the best system I’ve got my hands on. It got an extensive yet affordable lens lineup, and the portability plus IBIS makes it a travel-friendly system. Unfortunately, Panasonic and Olympus didn’t play the cards well. M43 systems are going to an end sooner than everyone thought. As much as I liked M43, I couldn’t invest more in a dying system. And this time, I went for the final mainstream brand I didn’t try before: Canon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Canon is being bashed all these years for its outdated sensor technology and I brought the least advanced of them, the Canon EOS RP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: center; width: 100%;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lightfocus-1256547063.cos.ap-hongkong.myqcloud.com/posts/photo-gears/RP.jpg&quot; style=&quot;margin: 0 auto; width: 50%;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This camera although has the same sensor as that on Canon 6D Mark II, is a more affordable model. While it’s entry-level and you could definitely tell from its build quality, at least you get a fully articulating screen and a comfortable grip.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: center; width: 100%;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lightfocus-1256547063.cos.ap-hongkong.myqcloud.com/posts/photo-gears/C24-105.jpg&quot; style=&quot;margin: 0 auto; width: 50%;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lenses I got with the camera were Canon RF 24-105 f/4 and Canon RF 35mm f/1.8 Macro. The 24-105mm is nothing special so I’ll skip it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: center; width: 100%;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lightfocus-1256547063.cos.ap-hongkong.myqcloud.com/posts/photo-gears/35%201.8.jpg&quot; style=&quot;margin: 0 auto; width: 50%;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 35mm lens, on the other hand, provides you 0.5x magnification in a consumer-level lens which is unseen before. This lens is relatively cheap and compact, but I really hated the noisy and slow AF system.
Another benefit with Canon mirrorless cameras is you get to use EF lenses in native AF speed. Therefore, I also got the chance to play with Canon EF 16-35mm f/2.8 L II, Canon EF 70-300mm f4-5.6 L, and Canon EF 100-400mm f/4.5-5.6 L II. All these lenses are superb except that 70-300mm is a bad copy but anyway I had some quite lovely pictures with them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I took a trip mainly for photography to Chongqing in late 2020 and I started to feel the importance of telephoto lenses in traveling. However, telephoto lenses are usually very heavy so we tend to leave them at home. Therefore I start to seek light telephoto lenses. While searching, one lens popped into my eyes: Tamron 28-200mm f/2.8-5.6. Yes, it’s a super zoom lens but hey, it’s compact and got a relatively bright aperture, and most importantly, its image quality is good for a super zoom lens. Some people complained but not having 24mm but for me, if 28mm isn’t wide enough, neither is 24mm. Just get yourself another wide-angle lens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And here we go again, I sold all Canon gears and got a Sony A7R3 and this Tamron 28-200mm lens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: center; width: 100%;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lightfocus-1256547063.cos.ap-hongkong.myqcloud.com/posts/photo-gears/A7R3.jpg&quot; style=&quot;margin: 0 auto; width: 50%;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: center; width: 100%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://lightfocus-1256547063.cos.ap-hongkong.myqcloud.com/posts/photo-gears/28-200.jpg&quot; style=&quot;margin: 0 auto; width: 50%;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was quite happy with this combo. I got the same, if not better, image quality as A7R2 while having better handling and battery life. And the quality of this lens is also quite satisfying. You get decent magnification, f/2.8 at 28mm and you can zoom all the way up to 200mm while this combo is just 1.2kg.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would say that A7R3 is the first camera I would not feel like ‘wanting for more’. For the next few years, I’d like to invest more in lenses. The Sony FE mount really has the best lens lineup right now, and I can’t wait to play some of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;– Update on 2021.9.6 –&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: center; width: 100%;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://lightfocus-1256547063.cos.ap-hongkong.myqcloud.com/posts/photo-gears/17-28.jpg&quot; style=&quot;margin: 0 auto; width: 50%;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I said before, having an ultra-wide lens is a good combo for 28-200 which is why I bought Tamron 17-28 f/2.8 lenses. It’s relatively cheap, has a constant f/2.8 aperture, and is really lightweight. It compromised on the focal range but it makes a perfect combo with 28-200 as there’s no overlapping between the two. With coverage from 17mm all the way to 200mm, it’s safe to say that they satisfy 95% of my photography. Not to mention the whole setup weighs only 1.7kg. I would only miss a third lens when I need more than 200mm but hey, I can always crop my image as I have 42 megapixels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, after using all these gears, I would like to do a sum-up. The following content refers to mirrorless cameras only.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Micro Four-Thirds:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a very fun system to play with. But it’s dying so I can’t recommend anyone to invest in it. If you got the money, definitely try it if you haven’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;APS-C:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Sony:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Awful handling, lack of IBIS, short battery life(except A6600). The good news is that now Tamron starts to make lenses for Sony APS-C cameras. You can now have Tamron 11-20 f/2.8, Tamron 17-70 f/2.8 paired with Sony own 70-350 f/4.5-6.3 G lenses and you’re all covered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Fujifilm:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Great for the beginner as it has good SOOC color and the dials on the top are good demonstrations of the basics of photography, let alone retro design. If you mainly play with RAW, I wouldn’t recommend it as X-Trans tends to be a bit soft compared to traditional Beyer Sensor. Also, lacking third-party lenses means you need to pay more money on the lenses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Canon:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While handling is better, it is the same as the Sony system where lenses are a real problem. I mean at least Sony APS-C users can use their full-frame lenses. Canon EF-M mount? That’s a joke. (Still, many people buy it for the color)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Full-frame:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Sony:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Handling and IBIS are average, the interface is terrible, but that’s basically it. Many affordable third-party lenses to choose from and the sensor image quality is top-notch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Canon:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Canon really knows how to make a comfortable grip and their glasses are the best in the class. If you got the budget or like the ‘Canon color’, go for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Nikon:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unless you got a bunch of Nikon F glass, I wouldn’t recommend it.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 06 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>/Revisit-on-photography-gears-Ive-used/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/Revisit-on-photography-gears-Ive-used/</guid>
        
        <category>Gear</category>
        
        
        <category>Photography</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>What Makes Apple Ecosystem So Special</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Whether you heard this before or not, Apple is famous for its ecosystem. Simply put, their devices tend to work together for better integrity. In this post, I’d like to introduce some of these features that build up the Apple ecosystem. If you happen to have a bunch of Apple devices in your hand, then you are in for a treat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Between multi-devices:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, iPhone is probably your first Apple device. And truth to be told, iPhone is the key to the Apple ecosystem because we do have iPhone exclusive features like phone calls and text messages. So the first thing that comes to mind would be calls and messages on iPads and Macs, which Apple calls &lt;a href=&quot;https://support.apple.com/en-us/HT209456&quot;&gt;iPhone Cellular Calls&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://support.apple.com/kb/HT208386&quot;&gt;Text Message Forwarding&lt;/a&gt;. Once set up, you may hear all your devices ring at the same time when you have an incoming call.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And there are more, like &lt;a href=&quot;https://support.apple.com/en-us/HT209460&quot;&gt;Universal Clipboard&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://support.apple.com/en-us/HT209455&quot;&gt;Handoff&lt;/a&gt;. The first one is pretty self-explained. As its name suggests, we can have a universal clipboard that shares between these devices, so you can copy something on your Mac and paste it on your iPhone. Handoff is rather interesting. If you opened a webpage and didn’t finish reading it, you can open it on your iPhone and pick up where you’ve left on the go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What if I want to send a file or a photo? No problem, use &lt;a href=&quot;https://support.apple.com/kb/HT203106&quot;&gt;AirDrop&lt;/a&gt;. It quickly finds what devices are around you. You simply tap the icon, and off you go. Best part? No data plan is needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While we’re talking about photos, why not enjoy them on a large TV screen? You can use &lt;a href=&quot;https://support.apple.com/en-us/HT204289&quot;&gt;AirPlay&lt;/a&gt; to mirror your iPhone or Mac screen on Apple TV. But AirPlay does more than that. For example, you can also share audio between devices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And for those who are forgetful, you can use the &lt;a href=&quot;https://support.apple.com/en-us/HT204085&quot;&gt;Keychain&lt;/a&gt; feature. It stores all your passwords, and you are just one autofill away from your passwords. This also works for Wi-Fi passwords. You can automatically connect to Wi-Fi if your other devices connected before.
Now, most of these features require an Apple ID with the free &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.icloud.com&quot;&gt;iCloud&lt;/a&gt; plan. If you’re willing to pay more, you can also use iCloud Drive, a cloud disk that allows you to store your files and get them instantly on any device.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t worry because we are far from completing this post. Now, let’s talk about features that are specific to some devices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Between iPhones and Apple Watches:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They’re born to be a pair. You get all &lt;a href=&quot;https://support.apple.com/en-us/HT204791&quot;&gt;notifications&lt;/a&gt; from your iPhone on your wrist. While the iPhone reads all health data on your watch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Between iPhones and Macs:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can use your iPhone’s camera to &lt;a href=&quot;https://support.apple.com/kb/HT209037&quot;&gt;take photos&lt;/a&gt; and import them directly to your Mac. Of course, you can also use your iPad, but I just feel more natural to take pictures on iPhones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Between iPad and Macs:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People like iPads for their large screens, so they’re perfect extensions for your Mac. That’s why with &lt;a href=&quot;https://support.apple.com/kb/HT210380&quot;&gt;Sidecar&lt;/a&gt;, you can mirror or extend your Mac desktop. One thing unique about iPads is you get to use Apple Pencil, a fantastic input device. Therefore, you can use the iPad as a drawing pad for Macs while extending the workspace on your Mac.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Between Apple Watch and Macs:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Say no more to your unlocking password. Your Apple Watch can &lt;a href=&quot;https://support.apple.com/kb/HT206995&quot;&gt;unlock&lt;/a&gt; your Mac when you’re near your Mac. This also works when the software is asking for the password. Simply double press the button on Apple Watch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So there you have it. Some of these features may not be Apple-exclusive but let’s be honest, Apple makes them more intuitive. As the slogan suggests: It just works.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 14 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>/What-Makes-Apple-Ecosystem-So-Special/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/What-Makes-Apple-Ecosystem-So-Special/</guid>
        
        <category>Technology</category>
        
        
        <category>Apple</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Photography 101</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Taking a photo on a smartphone may seem easy, but that’s because smartphones take care of many complicated things so you just need to press the button.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this post, I’d like to talk about some basics of photography so without the help of smartphones, you can still get some nice pictures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First things first, let’s talk about the ‘brightness’ of a photo, which we call ‘exposure’. If a photo is too dark, we call it ‘underexposed’, on the opposite, we call it ‘overexposed’. So what determines the exposure of a photo?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How much light you have of course. But in many situations, we can’t control the light source, but we can adjust our cameras to get the exposure we need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Three things affect your exposure: aperture, shutter speed, and ISO.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aperture is a hole-like mechanism in the lens that controls how much light will come through the lens. A smaller aperture means less light and vice versa. We describe aperture in f-numbers, something like f/1.4 or f/2. For a 50mm focal length lens, if its f-number is f/2, it means the hole for the light comes in is 50/2 = 25mm wide. Therefore, a smaller number actually means a bigger aperture. And every time the f-number is multiplied by the square root of 2 or roughly 1.4, the brightness is halved because only half the light can come in. For example, f/1 is two times brighter than f/1.4.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shutter speed means how long your shutter opens, the longer the shutter opens, the more light hits the sensor so your image will look brighter. The shutter is also used to control movement, a fast shutter can freeze movement while a slower shutter can cause motion blur.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ISO, aka sensitivity, measures how sensitive your sensor is to the light. No matter you’re shooting with a film or digital camera, the higher the ISO is, the more noise your image will have.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: center; width: 100%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://lightfocus-1256547063.cos.ap-hongkong.myqcloud.com/posts/photo-101/triangle.png&quot; style=&quot;margin: 0 auto; width: 80%;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These three things are in a triangle, so if one is changed, another has to be changed as well to maintain the same exposure. For example, in the same environment, a photo shot with f/1, 1/100 s, ISO 100 has the same exposure as a photo shot with f/2, 1/25 s, ISO 100. So there can be thousands of different combinations of these three values?
Yes, but we need to think about how these values will also affect things other than exposure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aperture also affects depth of field, or how much things are in focus in your photo. A bigger aperture results in a shallower depth of field which is good for portrait photos when you want to blur those backgrounds. A smaller aperture, however, makes more things in focus so it’s good for things like landscapes. Choose your aperture accordingly based on your topic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shutter speed, as we’ve talked about, affects movement. If you’re shooting sports or wildlife, you definitely want a fast shutter speed. A slower shutter speed is useful when you want to smooth a waterfall for example. One thing to keep in mind is that when you use a slower shutter speed, your handshake will likely ruin the photo. That’s why we need a tripod to stabilize your camera.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ISO will affect your image quality, so unless the former two things are limiting, don’t crank your ISO up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So there you have it, you’ve learned how to take a photo with the correct exposure if your camera doesn’t get the job done for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since autofocus is so advanced these days, I think I’ll just skip this part as beginners can rely on the autofocus without any concerns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last thing I’d like to address is composition, but I’ll not go too deep into this topic as this is a 101 lesson.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Composition is a term to describe how you arrange your subjects in your photo. Naturally, we’d like to put our subject in the center of the frame and that’s totally fine. It’s just that sometimes it can be quite boring to look at, so there’re plenty of ways to composite your photos, like the famous rule of thirds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now you know how to correct your exposure, control the depth of field and movement, you also have the concept of composition in your mind. Give them a try and see if you can take some different pictures.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 11 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>/Photography-101/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/Photography-101/</guid>
        
        <category>Technology</category>
        
        
        <category>Photography</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Introduction to Colors on Computers</title>
        <description>&lt;h2&gt;How to represent color&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Humans are bad at describing colors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: center; width: 100%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://lightfocus-1256547063.cos.ap-hongkong.myqcloud.com/posts/computer-color/Red.png&quot; style=&quot;margin: 0 auto; width: 50%;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the above example, most people will call it “red”. However, on the computer, they’re 4 different colors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’re many methods to represent colors on a computer, the best-known one is the RGB model. RGB model “adds” colors so you can represent any color by adding 3 primary colors in the light which are red, blue, and green. Why these 3 colors you may ask? Because these 3 colors can stimulate 3 different cone cells, but this does not mean that these colors are the most sensitive ones to the cells.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: center; width: 100%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://lightfocus-1256547063.cos.ap-hongkong.myqcloud.com/posts/computer-color/RGB_color_solid_cube.png&quot; style=&quot;margin: 0 auto; width: 50%;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;RGB model can be written in many ways. Take while as an example, you can represent it as (1.0,1.0,1.0), (255,255,255), (100%,100%,100%) etc. It’s obvious that the RGB model is related to the color space of the display devices. Different devices show RGB(255,255,255) in different color.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we consider an 8-bit device, RGB model in theory can display 256*256*256 = 16,777,216 colors. In some web pages, however, we use webpage safe colors which are dramatically less than 16 million colors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although the RGB model is prevalent, it has some disadvantages. The most obvious one is that it’s not intuitive to humans. For example, it’s hard for people to come up with the value of “yellow” unless you’re familiar with adding color. That’s why we’re having a new color model called “HSL/HSV”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: center; width: 100%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://lightfocus-1256547063.cos.ap-hongkong.myqcloud.com/posts/computer-color/Hsl-Hsv_models.png&quot; style=&quot;margin: 0 auto; width: 50%;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It may look a bit complex at the first glance, but it’s more intuitive. H stands for Hue, it’s a circle where you represent colors by the angle. S stands for saturation, the closer you’re to the center of the circle, the less saturation you have. V stands for Value or L stands for Lightness, the higher you’re in the cylinder, the more lightness you have. For example, (60°,1.0,1.0) means the most saturated yellow with maximum lightness. HSL/HSV model is more common in design, like color grading in photography will usually apply this model since it’s easier for people to understand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In most cases, HSL/HSV model is only used for presentation, when output to the display, we still apply the RGB model. Naturally, there’re equations to do that which we’re not going to discuss in this post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: center; width: 100%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://lightfocus-1256547063.cos.ap-hongkong.myqcloud.com/posts/computer-color/CMYK.png&quot; style=&quot;margin: 0 auto; width: 50%;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apart from that, there’s one more model that is commonly used, CMYK. This one is widely used in the printing industry where most printers only have four basic colors: black(K), cyan(C), magenta(M), and yellow(Y). Similarly, you can mix these 4 colors to get different colors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember we mentioned color space right? More people are probably more familiar with the word “Gamut”. Color space is defined by gamut and color model together. Many people mix the gamut and color space together since by default they mean RGB color model. Some common color spaces are sRGB, P3, Adobe RGB.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A common way to compare color space is to represent color spaces on a graph called “CIE1931 xy”. CIE1931 is the earliest color space using the mathematical definition in a 3D space. For simplicity, people project it on a 2D surface and using x and y to represent it, like a tongue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: center; width: 100%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://lightfocus-1256547063.cos.ap-hongkong.myqcloud.com/posts/computer-color/CIE1931xy.png&quot; style=&quot;margin: 0 auto; width: 50%;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The E point in the graph is called the “white point”. When we need to represent a color space, we only need to draw its border on the surface.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: center; width: 100%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://lightfocus-1256547063.cos.ap-hongkong.myqcloud.com/posts/computer-color/Colorspace.png&quot; style=&quot;margin: 0 auto; width: 50%;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last point I want to talk about is chroma subsampling which is widely used in compressing images or videos. How do we achieve that? We throw away some of the color information in an image or frame in a video since human eyes are more sensitive to brightness rather than color. By doing so, we can dramatically reduce the size of files without too many visual compromises.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: center; width: 100%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://lightfocus-1256547063.cos.ap-hongkong.myqcloud.com/posts/computer-color/Colorcomp.jpg&quot; style=&quot;margin: 0 auto; width: 80%;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, the first row looks basically the same, however, the second row looks different since the resolution of colors is different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chroma subsampling is usually represented in the format of “J:a:b” where J means the longer side of the area contains J pixels, the height of the area is 2 pixels, J is usually 4. a means how many colors are in the first row of the area, b means how many colors in the second row is different from those in the first row. Sometimes there’s a fourth value which is called Alpha, which means horizontal factor. You can ignore this value as it’s the same as J.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following graph shows some common chroma subsampling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: center; width: 100%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://lightfocus-1256547063.cos.ap-hongkong.myqcloud.com/posts/computer-color/Chroma_subsampling.png&quot; style=&quot;margin: 0 auto; width: 80%;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most compressed images and videos are using this method so the colors you see may not be the same as the original data.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 24 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>/Colors-on-Computers/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/Colors-on-Computers/</guid>
        
        <category>Technology</category>
        
        
        <category>Graphics</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Introduction to Git</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;As long as you work on computers, you’re likely running into a situation where you need to constantly modify a file or a folder. Problem is that when you want to check what it was like 3 days ago or you want to undo your modification, things will get tricky. That’s when version control comes to our aid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Git is a very popular distributed version control software. Note the word “distributed”, meaning that it will not only work locally on your computer but also can be used remotely. Since Git is a command-line based tool, you need to learn the syntax to make the best use of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before we dive into the commands, let’s take a look at the bigger picture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: center; width: 100%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://lightfocus-1256547063.cos.ap-hongkong.myqcloud.com/posts/git/git_operations.png&quot; style=&quot;margin: 0 auto; width: 80%;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we want to use Git in our project, go into the working folder and type in the command “git init” to initialize git so it knows the scope of which files need to be tracked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lightfocus-1256547063.cos.ap-hongkong.myqcloud.com/posts/git/git_init.png&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After initialization, we can use the command “git status” to verify the current status of git, which in this case, you can see all files haven’t been added to git. Whenever you want to check the status, you can use this command.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lightfocus-1256547063.cos.ap-hongkong.myqcloud.com/posts/git/git_status.png&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To add these files to git, we will use the command “git add .” where the dot means all files. This will add all files within the scope of git to the “stage” where you can later decide whether you want to add them into the branch. Alternatively, you can use “git add &amp;lt;filename&amp;gt;” to add the specific file you want to add.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lightfocus-1256547063.cos.ap-hongkong.myqcloud.com/posts/git/git_add.png&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once we confirm all files in the stage need to be committed to the branch, we type in “git commit -m your commit”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lightfocus-1256547063.cos.ap-hongkong.myqcloud.com/posts/git/git_commit.png&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;
If we use the command “git log”, we can see all the commits we’ve done so far.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lightfocus-1256547063.cos.ap-hongkong.myqcloud.com/posts/git/git_log.png&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since Git tracks all the commits, you can easily revert to the previous commit if you wish. Notice every commit has a long special number, we can use that number to clarify which commit we want to revert to. Type in “git reset &amp;lt;commit number&amp;gt;” and off you go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lightfocus-1256547063.cos.ap-hongkong.myqcloud.com/posts/git/git_reset.png&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another important feature of version control is to be able to work on different branches. If I have an idea but I’m not sure if it will be in the final project, I can use branches to experiment with my idea without affecting the master branch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By default, you’re working on the master branch. You can make new branches by typing “git branch &amp;lt;branchname&amp;gt;”. If you’re not sure which branch you’re working on, you can use the command “git branch” to check it out, the branch you’re on indicates by an asterisk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lightfocus-1256547063.cos.ap-hongkong.myqcloud.com/posts/git/git_branch.png&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To move between branches, type in “git checkout &amp;lt;branchname&amp;gt;”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lightfocus-1256547063.cos.ap-hongkong.myqcloud.com/posts/git/git_checkout.png&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you’re satisfied with your branch and want to merge it with the current branch, you can use the command “git merge &amp;lt;branchname&amp;gt;”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lightfocus-1256547063.cos.ap-hongkong.myqcloud.com/posts/git/git_merge.png&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now you know what to do when you add or modify files, more importantly when you want to undo the changes or make a branch. That wraps up the basics of git on your local computer. But remember we talked about “distributed”, so let’s talk about the remote capability of git next.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To simplify this post, we only talk about the most common commands you need to use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you want to publish your git project online, you first need to specify where you want to put by using the command “git remote add &amp;lt;name&amp;gt; &amp;lt;url&amp;gt;” where we used to name it “origin”, but choose your name anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After that, we need to push our git project to the Internet. Type in “git push &amp;lt;remote&amp;gt; &amp;lt;branch&amp;gt;” where &amp;lt;remote&amp;gt; is the name you give and &amp;lt;branch&amp;gt; specifies the branch you want to push, usually master.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, if we want to update our local project from the online repositories, we can use “git pull &amp;lt;remote&amp;gt;”. This will automatically merge the online files with your local files.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there is one more thing. What if we want to get a copy of other people’s git project? We can simply use “git clone &amp;lt;repo&amp;gt;” where &amp;lt;repo&amp;gt; is usually a URL of the repository ends with “.git”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to learn more about Git, here is the cheatsheet that you can work on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: center; width: 100%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://lightfocus-1256547063.cos.ap-hongkong.myqcloud.com/posts/git/git-cheatsheet-1.png&quot; style=&quot;margin: 0 auto; width: 80%;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: center; width: 100%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://lightfocus-1256547063.cos.ap-hongkong.myqcloud.com/posts/git/git-cheatsheet-2.png&quot; style=&quot;margin: 0 auto; width: 80%;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So there you have it. Now you can make use of the most popular version control software and hopefully it can make your life easier.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 21 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>/Introduction-to-Git/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/Introduction-to-Git/</guid>
        
        <category>Technology</category>
        
        
        <category>Software</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The history of Apple Silicons</title>
        <description>&lt;h1&gt;Before A series chip, there were...&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The original iPhone was announced in 2007 when the chip it uses was not developed by Apple. 4 chips were used in a variety of products before the introduction of the A4 chip in 2010.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;APL0098&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: center; width: 100%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://lightfocus-1256547063.cos.ap-hongkong.myqcloud.com/posts/apple-chip/APL0098.jpg&quot; style=&quot;margin: 0 auto; width: 50%;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;90mm chip, single-core, 412MHz frequency make this chip outdated but this is where the original iPhone started with. This chip was used on the original iPhone and iPhone 3G as well as the original iPod Touch. It’s worth mentioning that this is the only 16-bit chip in this post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;APL0278&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: center; width: 100%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://lightfocus-1256547063.cos.ap-hongkong.myqcloud.com/posts/apple-chip/APL0278.jpg&quot; style=&quot;margin: 0 auto; width: 50%;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was announced several mouthes after iPhone 3G and was used on the 2nd generation of iPod Touch. It’s basically an APL0098 with an updated process to 65 nm which reduces its die size to half and brings an even higher clock speed. The most important update is 32-bit memory addressing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;APL0298&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: center; width: 100%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://lightfocus-1256547063.cos.ap-hongkong.myqcloud.com/posts/apple-chip/APL0298.jpg&quot; style=&quot;margin: 0 auto; width: 50%;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Compared with the original chip, its clock speed is 50% higher, which proves the “S” in iPhone 3GS is “Speed”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;APL2298&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: center; width: 100%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://lightfocus-1256547063.cos.ap-hongkong.myqcloud.com/posts/apple-chip/APL2298.jpg&quot; style=&quot;margin: 0 auto; width: 50%;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last chip not designed by Apple, 45 nm process. Higher frequency brings the 3rd gen iPod Touch more performance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;This changes everything. Again.&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2010 comes the iPhone 4. Just like the ad says, iPhone 4 changes what a phone can do. Why? The Apple-designed chip definitely plays a big part in it. Moreover, no one knows what such a money-costing development can bring to Apple in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;A4&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: center; width: 100%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://lightfocus-1256547063.cos.ap-hongkong.myqcloud.com/posts/apple-chip/Apple-A4.jpg&quot; style=&quot;margin: 0 auto; width: 50%;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a lackluster chip if you look at its spec, same 45 nm process, slightly higher frequency, the biggest update is probably dual-channel memory. But don’t forget, iPhone 4 is the first product that utilizes Retina Display which has 4 times more pixels than the predecessor. This is a satisfying result.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;A5 &amp;amp; A5X&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lightfocus-1256547063.cos.ap-hongkong.myqcloud.com/posts/apple-chip/Apple-A5.png&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A5 focuses on one thing: performance. More than twice the die size brings the first dual-core chip designed by Apple. At the same time, GPU was upgraded to PowerVR SGX543MP2 which brings 7 times more performance, it’s unprecedented. If you remembered the keynote of the iPhone 4S, after the introduction of the A5 chip was the live demo of Infinity Blade II by Epic Games. Many desktop-level effects like particle effects, dynamic lighting were brought to mobile devices for the first time. This gives hope for future Apple chips. A5 also integrated an image signal processing unit for the first time which enhances the camera on iPhone 4S.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the story of A5 does not stop here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the Retina Display on iPhone was so popular, Apple wanted to bring this to the iPad. However, iPad has 5 times more pixels than iPhone which was not possible with the A5 chip.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Considering iPad has more physical room and a bigger battery, Apple decided to upgrade the GPU on A5. And here came the A5X which has double the GPU performance of that on A5. Ever since then, chips ended with X are made specifically for iPad with better GPU performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;A6 &amp;amp; A6X&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lightfocus-1256547063.cos.ap-hongkong.myqcloud.com/posts/apple-chip/Apple-A6.png&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a scheduled upgrade so not too many highlights except the 32 nm process. Due to the large time gap in production, newer A5 chips also had a 32 nm process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;World's first and only smartphone&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PC industrial spent many years to complete the transition from 32-bit to 64-bit, Apple took one generation of CPU.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;A7&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: center; width: 100%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://lightfocus-1256547063.cos.ap-hongkong.myqcloud.com/posts/apple-chip/Apple-A7.jpg&quot; style=&quot;margin: 0 auto; width: 50%;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;iPhone 5S had special meaning as it’s the world’s first smartphone with a 64-bit CPU. This proves Apple’s leadership in chip design, but also proves that Apple wanted to make its chips more professional.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Besides that, A7 also comes with M7, a co-op processor that can record sensor data without waking up A7. This allows recording health data without impact too much battery life. Since iPhone 5S is equipped with Touch ID, A7 also includes a secure enclave to protect fingerprint data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A7 may be too strong that Apple didn’t even release an A7X, but increased the frequency a bit and put it in the iPad Air.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;A8 &amp;amp; A8X&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lightfocus-1256547063.cos.ap-hongkong.myqcloud.com/posts/apple-chip/Apple-A8.png&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Normal update. Perhaps considered that iPhone 6’s large screen impacts battery life too much, A8 focused on energy-saving which only uses half power as A7.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;A9 &amp;amp; A9X&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lightfocus-1256547063.cos.ap-hongkong.myqcloud.com/posts/apple-chip/Apple-A9.png&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last generation of dual-core chips which means single-core performance was reaching its limit, so we need to use more cores in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A9 has two versions, 14 nm from Samsung and 16 nm from TSMC that were both used in iPhone. In Oct. 2015, a report said that the Samsung version has worse battery life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;A10 Fusion &amp;amp; A10X Fusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lightfocus-1256547063.cos.ap-hongkong.myqcloud.com/posts/apple-chip/Apple-A10.png&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To preserve even more battery life, Apple for the first time used a big-small core architecture. 2 + 2 core configuration makes A10 have better battery life under light tasks. However, big and small cores cannot be used at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Take it to the next level.&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2017 marks the 10th anniversary of the iPhone, Apple announced iPhone X. The headline feature was of course Face ID. To achieve high security, Apple had to change its chip design again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;A11 Bionic&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: center; width: 100%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://lightfocus-1256547063.cos.ap-hongkong.myqcloud.com/posts/apple-chip/Apple-A11.jpg&quot; style=&quot;margin: 0 auto; width: 50%;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before A11, Apple only designs the CPU part, GPU still uses chips by PowerVR. This time, Apple makes both. Besides that, Apple added a neural engine in A11 which enabled hardware acceleration for deep learning. A new controller allows big and small cores to work at the same time which improves performance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;A12 Bionic &amp;amp; A12X Bionic&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lightfocus-1256547063.cos.ap-hongkong.myqcloud.com/posts/apple-chip/Apple-A12.png&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The neural engine made many new features possible and that’s why Apple updated it to enable 5000 billion calculations per second. A12 is also the first 7 nm chip used on the smartphone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;A13 Bionic&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: center; width: 100%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://lightfocus-1256547063.cos.ap-hongkong.myqcloud.com/posts/apple-chip/Apple-A13.jpg&quot; style=&quot;margin: 0 auto; width: 50%;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, iPhone has a one-year advantage over Android phones in terms of performance. Sometimes it’s even closer to the desktop performance. Since Apple can integrate more functions into a chip, a dream 10 years ago is slowly becoming the reality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Those long divided shall be united.&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The world is unpredictable, Apple could have not imagined this 10 years ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;A12Z Bionic&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;June 24, 2010, iPhone 4 went on sale, marks the release of the first Apple-designed chip. 10 years later, on June 22, 2020, on WWDC 2020, Apple announced that future Macs will also use Apple-designed chips. The A12Z inside DTK is only one more GPU core than the A12X.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: center; width: 100%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://lightfocus-1256547063.cos.ap-hongkong.myqcloud.com/posts/apple-chip/ADTK.png&quot; style=&quot;margin: 0 auto; width: 50%;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Demo on WWDC is fairly promising as tasks like video editing, 3D rendering, and games are all working fluidly. Future chips will for sure be better than A12Z, so it’s very exciting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking back this 10 years, Apple made some exciting products with these chips. Apple probably only wants to apply their chips on iPhone in the very beginning, but as time goes by, Apple found that their chips were capable of doing many things, which led Apple to control all their production with Apple-designed chips.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;– Update on Sept. 6, 2021 –&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;M1 chip used on the MacBook Air and MacBook Pro seems like a success as people found its performance amazing. The problem with M1 is mainly the lack of I/O and memory which shows this is an entry-level chip. I’m looking forward to the M2 chip that may come later this year.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 21 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>/Apple-Silicons/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/Apple-Silicons/</guid>
        
        <category>Technology</category>
        
        
        <category>Apple</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Mac选购指南</title>
        <description>&lt;h4&gt;最后更新于2020.8.19&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;在选购Mac之前，我们首先应该问问自己为什么要买Mac。如果不是因为macOS或者 logo的话，Windows阵营有更好的选择。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apple在WWDC2020上宣布将于2020年开始由Intel Mac向Apple Silicon Mac过渡，为期两年，因此在这个时候购买Mac就成了一件麻烦事。如果你对Apple Silicon不熟悉的话，其实就是Apple一直在自家iPhone和iPad上用的自己研发的芯片。关于更多Apple Silicon的介绍和更换Apple Silicon能给Mac带来什么优势，可以移步&lt;a href=&quot;https://lightfocus.github.io/blog/Apple-Silicon&quot;&gt;这里&lt;/a&gt;。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;简单来说，我的选择原则如下：&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;选择Intel Mac如果你：&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1.购买Mac是刚需&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2.需要在Mac上运行Windows&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;等待Apple Silicon Mac如果你：&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1.想获得更长的系统更新支持&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2.主要用Mac进行视频图像处理&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;确定了你需要一台Mac以后，我们可以利用下表根据自己的预算以及对便携性的需求快速选择出适合自己的机型。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;table-container&quot;&gt;
&lt;table class=&quot;table&quot;&gt;
&lt;thead class=&quot;table-header&quot;&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th class=&quot;header-item&quot;&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th class=&quot;header-item&quot;&gt;性能较弱&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th class=&quot;header-item&quot;&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th class=&quot;header-item&quot;&gt;性能强劲&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;tabel-row&quot;&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;笔记本&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;MacBook Air&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;MacBook Pro 13'&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;MacBook Pro 16'&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;tabel-row&quot;&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;台式机&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;Mac Mini&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;iMac 21.5' / 27'&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;iMac Pro / Mac Pro&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;tabel-row&quot;&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;预算范围&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;¥10000&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;¥10000-16000&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;¥19000&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;tabel-row&quot;&gt;
&lt;td colspan=&quot;4&quot; class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;注：Mac Mini &amp;amp; Mac Pro不带显示器&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;当然，因为每种机型里面还有不同的配置可选，所以下文详细展开每一项配置应该怎么选。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;处理器：&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;适合下列任务：编译、视频编码解码&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;推荐升级机型：MacBook Air的双核i3升级到四核i5（仅¥500），台式机根据自己需求升级&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;不推荐升级机型：所有MacBook Pro，价格高且因为散热问题性能提升有限&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;内存：&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;适合下列任务：基本上所有任务，尤其是涉及到多开或者大型应用的情况，例如Chrome、FCPX&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;推荐升级机型：所有机型，对于经常修图、剪视频、写代码以及需要虚拟机的建议16G起步&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;存储设备：&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;适合下列任务：所有松鼠囤积病患者&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;推荐升级机型：所有机型，如果需要装Windows建议至少512G起步&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;图形处理器（仅针对16寸MacBook Pro及除了Mac Mini的台式机）：&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;适合下列任务：视频编码加速、游戏&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;推荐升级机型：除了Mac Pro上的高配显卡，其他性能都很一般，根据自己需求升级&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;其他：&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;以太网（Mac Mini）：一般家庭用户没必要&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Afterburner（Mac Pro）：到这个级别了应该很清楚自己的需求了&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;妙控鼠标和妙控板（台式机）：妙控鼠标手感不好、强烈建议妙控板+其他鼠标&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;预装软件：有学生资格的话五件套只要¥1298！&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;一些简单对比&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;4 Core MacBook Air vs 2 Thunderbolt MacBook Pro&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;table-container&quot;&gt;
&lt;table class=&quot;table&quot;&gt;
&lt;thead class=&quot;table-header&quot;&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th class=&quot;header-item&quot;&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th class=&quot;header-item&quot;&gt;4C MacBook Air&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th class=&quot;header-item&quot;&gt;2TB MacBook Pro&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;table-row&quot;&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;CPU&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;Intel Core i5 1030NG7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;Intel Core i5 8257U&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;table-row&quot;&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;内存&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;8G 3733 MHz&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;8G 2133 MHz&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;table-row&quot;&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;显卡&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;Iris Plus G7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;Iris Plus 645&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;table-row&quot;&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;固态硬盘&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;256G&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;256G&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;table-row&quot;&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;重量&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;1.29 kg&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;1.4 kg&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;table-row&quot;&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;价格&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;8499&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;9999&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;乍一看好像MacBook Air便宜1500而且性能差不多，不过我们还是详细谈一谈二者的区别。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CPU方面，MacBook Pro还是强一些，Cinebench R15单核 159 vs 140，多核 638 vs 448。另外MacBook Air的散热是一个很大的问题，因为内部风扇和CPU之间没有直连，所以这个风扇相当于只是把空气吸入内部，然后CPU被动散热。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;显卡两者差距不大，MacBook Pro小胜一筹。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;屏幕方面，MacBook Pro支持P3色域而且亮度可达500nit，MacBook Air只支持sRGB色域而且亮度只有400nit，MacBook Pro完胜。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;扬声器效果MacBook Pro好一些。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;可能是因为电池比MacBook Pro小（58.2Wh vs 49.9Wh），MacBook Air的续航在浏览网页等轻量工作时稍短于MacBook Pro。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;总结：这1500的差距主要体现在TouchBar、屏幕、扬声器以及更好的散热（虽然是五十步笑百步）。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;2 Thunderbolt MacBook Pro 13' vs 4 Thunderbolt MacBook Pro 13'&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;简单来说，只要预算到位，强烈建议上4 Thunderbolt的MAcBook Pro，主要原因如下：&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1、十代CPU vs 八代CPU&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2、16G内存 512G固态硬盘起步&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3、2个Thunderbolt口真的不够用&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;iMac Pro vs Mac Pro&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;两者还是有很大一段价格重叠，不过定位完全不同。iMac Pro针对不喜欢折腾、桌面空间有限以及喜欢开箱即用的用户，后期扩展升级性低。而Mac Pro针对需要很强扩展性的用户，或者是那些需要自己选配顶级显示器的用户。&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 19 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>/Which-Mac-to-Buy/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/Which-Mac-to-Buy/</guid>
        
        <category>Gear</category>
        
        
        <category>Apple</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>自己装机硬件怎么选？</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;装一台电脑可能对于很多人来说不是一件容易事，但其实它真的很简单。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;本文先从最基本的硬件选购开始，介绍各个硬件、教你如何判断一个硬件的性能，以及选购的时候需要注意的事项。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;一、CPU&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;CPU作为电脑的大脑，肯定是要好好选。能选择的有两家：Intel、AMD，俗称红蓝厂。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;del&gt;自古红蓝出CP&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Intel和AMD可以说是老冤家了，从上个世纪就开始CPU市场的竞争，什么第一个64位处理器啊，第一个突破1GHz主频的CPU啊。在很长一段时间里，Intel都是吊打AMD的，只有便宜的电脑才会装AMD的CPU。而今天的故事还要从2014年说起。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2014年10月27日，Intel发布了Broadwell处理器，用上了14nm的制程。在处理器制程上的更新，Intel一直都是采用Tick-Tock策略，即一代提升制程，下一代优化，再下一代再提升制程，以此类推。例如：Penryn(45nm)-&amp;gt;Nehalem(45nm)-&amp;gt;Westmere(32nm)-&amp;gt;Sandy Bridge(32nm)。从22nm的Haswell开始，Intel变成了Tick-Tock-Refresh的策略，也就是说一个制程用三年。但是让人没想到的是，2014年发布的14nm处理器，竟然让Intel用了Broadwell、Skylake、Kaby Lake、Kaby Lake R、Coffee Lake、Amber Lake、Comet Lake整整六代（我没有数错）处理器上。Intel自此也被人称为“牙膏厂”，因为新制程一直挤不出来。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AMD这边则是通过2017年发布的基于Zen架构的Ryzen开始翻身，从以前的性价比首选，到高端电脑也可以选。尤其是2019年发布的3代Ryzen，基于Zen2机构，赶在Intel之前实现了7nm制程。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;因此，在Intel挤出桌面10nm牙膏之前，装机我&lt;strong&gt;个人推荐&lt;/strong&gt;AMD的处理器。不过Intel的处理器在游戏方面可能更胜一筹，但是两者差距只有在100+fps时才体现的出来（即需要顶级显卡）。装黑苹果建议选择Intel。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;选购CPU主要关注以下几个参数：&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;核心数：顾名思义，核心的数量，越多越快&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;线程数：一般等于核心数，具有超线程功能的CPU则等于核心数的两倍。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;基准频率：一般运行的频率，越高速度越快&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Boost频率：可以波动频率的最高值（非手动超频情况下）&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;TDP：热设计功耗，和散热及电源的选择密切相关&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;下面列出Zen2架构的CPU（不包含HEDT平台）&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;table-container&quot;&gt;
&lt;table class=&quot;table&quot;&gt;
&lt;thead class=&quot;table-header&quot;&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th class=&quot;header-item&quot;&gt;型号&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th class=&quot;header-item&quot;&gt;售价MSRP($)&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th class=&quot;header-item&quot;&gt;核心数/线程数&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th class=&quot;header-item&quot;&gt;基准频率(GHz)&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th class=&quot;header-item&quot;&gt;Boost频率(GHz)&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th class=&quot;header-item&quot;&gt;TDP(W)&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;tabel-row&quot;&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot; colspan=&quot;6&quot;&gt;入门级&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;tabel-row&quot;&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;3100&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;99&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;4/8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;3.6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;3.9&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;65&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;tabel-row&quot;&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;3300X&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;120&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;4/8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;3.8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;4.3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;65&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;tabel-row&quot;&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot; colspan=&quot;6&quot;&gt;主流级&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;tabel-row&quot;&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;3500X&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;￥1099&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;6/6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;3.6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;4.1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;65&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;tabel-row&quot;&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;3600&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;199&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;6/12&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;3.6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;4.2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;65&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;tabel-row&quot;&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;3600X&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;249&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;6/12&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;3.8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;4.4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;95&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;tabel-row&quot;&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;3600XT&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;249&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;6/12&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;3.8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;4.5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;95&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;tabel-row&quot;&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot; colspan=&quot;6&quot;&gt;性能级&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;tabel-row&quot;&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;3700X&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;329&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;8/16&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;3.6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;4.4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;65&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;tabel-row&quot;&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;3800X&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;399&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;8/16&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;3.9&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;4.5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;105&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;tabel-row&quot;&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;3800XT&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;399&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;8/16&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;3.9&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;4.7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;105&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;tabel-row&quot;&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot; colspan=&quot;6&quot;&gt;发烧级&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;tabel-row&quot;&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;3900X&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;499&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;12/24&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;3.8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;4.6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;105&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;tabel-row&quot;&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;3900XT&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;499&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;12/24&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;3.8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;4.7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;105&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;tabel-row&quot;&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;3950X&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;749&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;16/32&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;3.5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;4.7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;105&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;建议预算4000以内装机的用户选择3300X，6000左右的选择3600，10000左右选择3700X。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;二、主板&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;选好CPU的同时也就确定了主板可选的范围。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;以3代Ryzen为例，其接口为AM4，通过查询我们可以得知支持该接口的芯片组有：&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;table-container&quot;&gt;
&lt;table class=&quot;table&quot;&gt;
&lt;thead class=&quot;table-header&quot;&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th class=&quot;header-item&quot;&gt;型号&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th class=&quot;header-item&quot;&gt;PCI Express (PCIe)&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th class=&quot;header-item&quot;&gt;市场定位&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th class=&quot;header-item&quot; colspan=&quot;4&quot;&gt;CPU 支持&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;table-row&quot;&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;芯片组PCIe 通道数&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;Zen&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;Zen+&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;Zen 2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;Zen 3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;table-row&quot;&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;X570&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;PCIe 4.0 ×16&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot; rowspan=&quot;3&quot;&gt;性能级&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;否&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot; rowspan=&quot;3&quot;&gt;是&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot; rowspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;是&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;是&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;table-row&quot;&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;X470&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot; rowspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;PCIe 2.0 ×8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot; rowspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;是&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot; rowspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;否&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;table-row&quot;&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;X370&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;需要BIOS 升级&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;B550&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;PCIe 3.0 ×6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot; rowspan=&quot;3&quot;&gt;主流级&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;否&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;否&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot; rowspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;是&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;是&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;table-row&quot;&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;B450&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot; rowspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;PCIe 2.0 ×6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot; rowspan=&quot;3&quot;&gt;是&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot; rowspan=&quot;3&quot;&gt;是&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot; rowspan=&quot;3&quot;&gt;否&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;table-row&quot;&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;B350&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot; rowspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;需要BIOS 升级&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;table-row&quot;&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;A320&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;PCIe 2.0 ×4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;入门级&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;不同芯片组的功能、可扩展性、对未来CPU的支持都不一样。对于可能要升级Zen3的用户值得考虑X570和B550，否则一般用户X470和B450也足够了，因为AM4接口只用到Zen3为止。后面更新的CPU又是新的接口要买新的主板。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;除了芯片组以外，主板还有一个很关键的参数就是板型。板型决定了主板的大小以及接口数量。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;常见的主板板型有：ATX（305mm*244mm）、microATX（244mm*244mm）、Mini-ITX（170mm*170mm）。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;想要装一台体积小巧的电脑最佳选择肯定是Mini-ITX的主板，不过Mini-ITX主板一般价格稍贵而且通常只有个一个PCIe接口，所以Crossfire或者SLI就肯定不行了。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;一般来说建议CPU和主板一起买，价格会比较优惠，而且对于部分老主板可以让卖家帮你刷好新的BIOS以保证CPU能正常工作。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;三、显卡&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;独立显卡并不是人人都需要。对于不需要太强劲显卡性能同时想省钱的用户可以考虑Intel带集成显卡的CPU或者AMD的APU系列，即把显卡集成在CPU里面。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;目前3代Ryzen能买到的APU好像只有Ryzen 5 3400G。购买APU需要注意两个问题：1、APU的性能与内存息息相关，买APU的用户一定不能在内存上省钱 2、APU对黑苹果的支持有问题。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;那么剩下的用户自然就是需要高性能独立显卡的了。类似的，独立显卡市场也是两大阵营，AMD和NVIDIA，俗称红绿厂，也是老冤家，这里就不展开叙述了。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AMD的显卡没有像它的CPU那么猛，吊打竞争对手。在高端显卡这块，还是NVIDIA一家独大。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AMD这边你能买到最好的显卡就是RX 5700 XT，略逊于NVIDIA的RTX 2070 Super。但是NVIDIA往上还有2080、2080super、2080ti呢。（这里不讨论Titan以及Vega II Duo）&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;新显卡的独家功能上，NVIDIA更吸引人。光线追踪、DLSS以及CUDA，AMD这边只有RIS比较有看头。注意：GTX 16xx显卡不支持光线追踪及DLSS。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;关于上面功能的介绍请移步&lt;a href=&quot;https://lightfocus/github.io/blog/intro-ray-tracing&quot;&gt;这里&lt;/a&gt;。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;下面给出热门在售显卡的参考性能，可以根据实时价格对比购买。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GTX 1650 参考性能：&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PUBG(1080p Ultra): 60 fps&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gears 5(1080p High): 60 fps&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Assassin’s Creed Odyssey(1080p Very High): 47 fps&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Metro Exodus(1080p High): 46 fps&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Red Dead Redemption 2(1080p Medium-High): 37 fps&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Battlefield 5(1080p Ultra): 54 fps&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Control(1080p High): 32 fps&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;table-container&quot;&gt;
&lt;table class=&quot;table&quot;&gt;
&lt;thead class=&quot;table-header&quot;&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th class=&quot;header-item&quot;&gt;型号&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th class=&quot;header-item&quot;&gt;相对性能（1080p）&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;table-row&quot;&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#00ff00;&quot;&gt;GTX 1650&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#00ff00;&quot;&gt;100%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;table-row&quot;&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#ff0000;&quot;&gt;RX 570&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#ff0000;&quot;&gt;114%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;table-row&quot;&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#ff0000;&quot;&gt;RX 5500&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#ff0000;&quot;&gt;129%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;table-row&quot;&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#ff0000;&quot;&gt;RX 580&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#ff0000;&quot;&gt;131%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;table-row&quot;&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#ff0000;&quot;&gt;RX 5500 XT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#ff0000;&quot;&gt;132%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;table-row&quot;&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#00ff00;&quot;&gt;GTX 1650 Super&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#00ff00;&quot;&gt;135%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;table-row&quot;&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#00ff00;&quot;&gt;GTX 1660&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#00ff00;&quot;&gt;150%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;table-row&quot;&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#00ff00;&quot;&gt;GTX 1660 Super&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#00ff00;&quot;&gt;168%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;table-row&quot;&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#00ff00;&quot;&gt;GTX 1660 Ti&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#00ff00;&quot;&gt;172%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;table-row&quot;&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#00ff00;&quot;&gt;RTX 2060&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#00ff00;&quot;&gt;202%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;table-row&quot;&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#ff0000;&quot;&gt;RX 5700&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#ff0000;&quot;&gt;210%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;table-row&quot;&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#00ff00;&quot;&gt;RTX 2060 Super&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#00ff00;&quot;&gt;227%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;table-row&quot;&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#00ff00;&quot;&gt;RTX 2070&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#00ff00;&quot;&gt;235%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;table-row&quot;&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#ff0000;&quot;&gt;RX 5700 XT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#ff0000;&quot;&gt;241%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;table-row&quot;&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#00ff00;&quot;&gt;RTX 2070 Super&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#00ff00;&quot;&gt;260%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;table-row&quot;&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#00ff00;&quot;&gt;RTX 2080&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#00ff00;&quot;&gt;277%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;table-row&quot;&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#00ff00;&quot;&gt;RTX 2080 Super&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#00ff00;&quot;&gt;294%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;table-row&quot;&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#00ff00;&quot;&gt;RTX 2080 Ti&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class=&quot;table-data&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#00ff00;&quot;&gt;324%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;在你选好了显卡以后，你会发现同一个型号，不同厂家的价格差距很大。同一型号内便宜的称为乞丐版，贵的称为顶级非公版。乞丐版会在供电、RGB以及散热上缩水，同时显卡的频率不如顶级非公版的高。在预算不足又想要高性能的前提下可以买丐版。例如2070 super丐版3300，顶级非公4000出头，但是2080super的丐版只要4300。这种情况下选择2080super丐版能获得更好的性能。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;四、内存&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;不考虑上古DDR3的话，买内存就三个重要指标：容量、频率、时序。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;容量建议起步16G，上限看你插槽数量和钱包了。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;频率对高帧率游戏以及APU影响明显，建议3200MHz往上。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;对于Zen2架构的用户特别注意，3733MHz是内存延迟的Sweet Spot：&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lightfocus-1256547063.cos.ap-hongkong.myqcloud.com/posts/hardware/ryzen3memory.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Ryzen3Memory&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;时序介绍起来比较复杂，对新手来说，记得第一位数字越小越好。因此3600MHz C16的内存比3600MHz C18的内存好。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;del&gt;RGB内存条性能翻倍&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;五、硬盘&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;大体上分为三类：机械硬盘，SATA固态硬盘，NVMe固态硬盘&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;机械硬盘：使用SATA接口，内部是磁盘的传统硬盘，速度约100mb/s。&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;优点：容量大，数据可以恢复&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;缺点：需要额外供电、体积大且重、抗震性差&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;SATA固态硬盘：使用SATA接口，内部是闪存的固态硬盘，速度约500mb/s。&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;优点：不需要占用主板的m.2接口&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;缺点：需要额外供电、价格稍高&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;NVMe固态硬盘：使用m.2接口，内部是闪存的固态硬盘，速度约1gb/s-3gb/s。&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;优点：速度很快&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;缺点：温度高、主板m.2口有限、价格较高&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;六、电源&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;如果是ITX小机箱，那大概率只能买ITX电源，贵且选择少，推荐海盗船SF系列。另外小机箱可能不好走线，还需要买电源定制线。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;功率看你的硬件，例如CPU TDP 100W，显卡 TDP 200W 那最好买550W以上的电源。预算够的话功率尽可能买大一点，这个功率不是指电脑耗电功率，而是电源最大能输出的功率，大一点风险低而且后面升级硬件方便。当然太便宜又号称高功率的电源你自己看着办吧。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;电源转化效率有80PLUS的等级，即什么铜牌、银牌、金牌电源。看预算，没必要强上。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;七、机箱&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;可以没有，散热性最好；或者奢侈一点，拿个鞋盒（逃）。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;看着你喜欢的买就行，注意支持的板型。一些ITX小机箱会对CPU散热器限高、显卡限长、限高。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;八、散热器&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;买盒装CPU一般会送一个风扇，不建议使用，温度压不住。有条件上水冷，没条件也买一个好一点的风冷。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;注意机箱限高。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;猫扇是信仰，贵但是不一定好。&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 19 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
        <link>/What-Hardware-to-Buy/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/What-Hardware-to-Buy/</guid>
        
        <category>Gear</category>
        
        
        <category>Hardware</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
